Guide to the Collection of Bookplates by Alfred Cossmann
Yale University Arts Library
Collection of Bookplates by Alfred Cossmann
1902-1944
BKP 70
Yale University Arts Library
1.25
(3 boxes)
The collection contains bookplates by Alfred Cossmann, an Austrian graphic artist and engraver.
Cossmann, Alfred, 1870-1951
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Yale Bookplate Collection was formerly housed in Sterling Memorial Library. The collection was incorporated into the Arts of the Book Collection in 1984 and then moved to the Seeley G. Mudd Library in 1990. In 2011 it was transferred to the Robert B. Haas Family Arts Library.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Alfred Cossmann (1870-1951) was an Austrian graphic artist and engraver, active in Vienna during the first half of the 20th century and well known for his bookplate designs.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains bookplates by Alfred Cossmann, an Austrian graphic artist and engraver. In addition to ex-libris, the collection also contains a variety of greeting cards and other illustrations by Cossmann.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Bookplates – Individuals. II. Bookplates – Duplicates. III. Other Works. IV. Ephemera.
Any correspondence or ephemeral materials relating to a specific bookplate are filed together with the bookplate.
Bookplates; Bookplates; Greeting cards; Cossmann, Alfred, 1870-1951
- Bookplates – Individuals, Series I
  Arrangement
  Arranged in alphabetical order by the patron's last name.
  - Adamus – Blaschek, 1902-1940 undated; 7 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bloch-Bauer – Cossmann, 1904-1930 undated; 10 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Scope and Contents
    This folder contains examples of the artist's own bookplate designs.
  - von Dalberg – Emmrich, 1912-1923 undated; 9 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Fasal – Habsburg-Lothringen, 1904-1931 undated; 9 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    This folder contains two bookplate designs for the Archduke of Austria, Erzherzog Eugen von Habsburg-Lothringen (1863-1954).
  - Hediger – Kreuzenstein, 1911-1941 undated; 10 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Krieger – Morecki, 1910-1922 undated; 8 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Motog – Reichert, 1908 1938 undated; 9 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Reinle – Schweinburg, 1907-1942 undated; 8 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Stolz – Teltscher, 1908-1935 undated; 10 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Along with the bookplates of Franz Stuchlik, this folder also contains a card with a description of one of those designs.
  - Tucker-Lüscher – Zillich, 1932-1938 undated; 13 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Bookplates – Duplicates, Series II
  This series contains bookplates identified as duplicates of those found in Series I; however, these duplicate bookplates often vary in the size and type of paper or the color of ink printed. They also show evidence of different collectors' marks and occasional inscriptions.
  - Adamus – Fasal, [1905] 1911 1913 undated; 21 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Fischoff – Kreuzenstein, 1914 undated; 21 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Lemberger – Probst, undated; 21 items (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Reichert – Stuchlik, 1930 1934 undated; 22 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Suess – Zillich, 1908 1911 1936 undated; 22 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Other Works, Series III
  This series contains works by Cossmann other than ex-libris designs. These include various greeting cards as well as other examples of graphic design.
  - Anniversary Cards, 1921; 2 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    This folder contains a commemorative card celebrating 50 years of the Gesellschaft für vervielfältigende Kunst, or the Society for Reproductive Art, in Vienna.
  - Holiday Cards, 1915 1925; 2 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    General note
    This folder contains a New Year's card as well as one for Easter.
  - Illustrations with Quotes, 1934-1943; 5 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    This folder contains cards with various illustrations and quotes, including Meister Eckart ("Wer ungetrübt und lauter sein will, der muß eines haben: Abgeschiedenheit."); Shakespeare ("Das Recht soll nicht zur Vogelscheuche werden, als stünd es da, um Habichte zu schrecken, und bleibe regungslos, bis sie zuletzt gewöhnt, drauf ausruhn, statt zu fliehn."); Goethe ("Der kleine Gott der Welt bleibt stets von gleichem Schlag, und ist so wunderlich als wie am ersten Tag."); and the "Deutschlandlied" by August Heinrich Hoffmann von Fallersleben.
  - Memorial Card, 1945; 1 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    This folder contains a memorial card for Marie Stosius (August 25, 1889 - March 3, 1944).
  - Thank-you Card, undated; 1 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    This folder contains a thank-you card designed by and also from Alfred Cossmann.
  - Visiting Card, 1916; 1 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    This folder contains a visiting card for Anna Cossmann-Wettengl.
  - Zodiac Cards, undated; 2 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    This folder contains cards for Aquarius and Aries.
- Ephemera, Series IV
  - Cossmann list; exhibition label, undated; 2 (Box 3, Folder 23)